Since we would like our algorithm to generalize to unseen dataset during training,
we're going to focus on the performance of our algorithm on the test dataset.
In particular, we are interested in
the test error which is the error rate of our model on the test dataset.
The test error can be decomposed into three terms.
The variance, the bias,
and epsilon which we will ignore for the moment.
The variance describes the amount by which
our model's parameters would change if we were to change the training data.
The bias describes how good our model is given the training data.
To minimize the test error,
we need to minimize both of bias and the variance which
means that we need our model to both perform well on the training data and the test data.
However, by minimizing the bias,
we tend to increase the variance because we are over-fitting the training data set.
Let's look at an example together.
We are fitting a model on
a particular dataset and we can control the complexity of this model.
For example, by increasing the number of parameters.
Well, as the model becomes more complex,
the bias in red decreases.
Our model has more capacity to fit the training data.
However, the variance in purple increases with the complexity as
our model becomes more and more specialized to
this dataset and loses its capacity to generalize.
If we sum both terms,
we obtain the test error in blue.
The blue curves show the existence of
an optimal complexity where the test error is minimized.
Well, this is what we call the bias-variance trade-off.
You want your model to be complex enough to have
a low bias but not too complex so that you can still generalize to unseen data.